Guide to the Clell Thorpe World War II Photographs
University of Houston Libraries
Clell Thorpe World War II Photographs
1941-1960
10/1971-003
Thorpe, Clell
2.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Other Information: Uploaded to TARO, 2005. Additional information may be found at https://txarchives.org/uhsc/finding_aids/00003.xml
The bulk of this collection dates from the years 1943 through 1945. The collection mainly contains black and white photographs taken by Clell Thorpe, as well as some 4x5" negatives, one letter, one manuscript, and some miscellaneous items.
Biographical Information:
Clell Thorpe served as a Marine Corps photographer documenting the activities of Marines in the South Pacific during World War II. During the period [1944?]-1945, he traveled to several islands that had been taken from Japanese in earlier battles, such as Tarawa (captured in November 1943) and Kwajalein (captured on February 1944).
In 1943, Thorpe trained as a Marine Corps photographer at the Naval School of Photography in Pensacola, FL (the Marine Corps is administratively part of the U.S. Navy).
One of Thorpe's assignments involved photographing the Marine Bombing Squadron (VMB-613). The squadron trained in Boca Chica, Florida and Newport, Arkansas during 1944, then went to the home base for the VMB-613 as the squadron participated in operations in the Marshall Island throughout the war.
Thorpe took many photographs on a Pacific atoll in the Marshall Islands, which was not identified due to wartime censorship.
Thorpe also photographed on Tarawa Island in 1945.
Thorpe is known to have lived in Houston, Texas during 1947, and probably other years.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms
Genre/Form of Material:
Photographs
Personal Name:
Thorpe, Clell
Topical Term:
World War, 1939-1945
Acquisition Information:
This collection was donated to the UH Libraries by Clell Thorpe in 1971.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Related Materials:
Marine Bombing Squadron (VMB-613) Photographs digital collection http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/p15195coll10
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection dates from the years 1943 through 1945. The collection mainly contains black and white photographs taken by Clell Thorpe, as well as some 4x5" negatives, one letter, one manuscript, and some miscellaneous items.
The material is arranged in five series: Naval School of Photography, Marine Bombing Squadron (VMB-613), Pacific Atoll, Tarawa, and Miscellaneous.
Detailed List of Contents
- Naval School of Photography
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains black and white photographs taken at the Naval School of Photography in Pensacola, FL. The series includes pictures of airplanes, the Naval Air Station in Pensacola, and Clell Thorpe himself.
  - approximately 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - June 19, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oct. 25, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - approximately 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4-34)
  - Aug. 28, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - approximately 1943 (Box 1, Folder 36-40)
- Marine Bombing Squadron 613 (VMB-613), approximately 1944-1945
  One hundred forty-one black and white photographs document life for the Marine Bombing Squadron 613 (VMB-613), probably on Kwajalein Island. Subjects include various buildings used by the squadron, the men in various departments such as the Engineering Department and the Medical Department, and squadron sports teams. Also included are photographs of planes with their crews, and planes flying with a convoy near Eniwetok Atol.
  - Administration (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bakery (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Barber Shop (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ordinance Bomb Crew (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Commanding Officer (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Preparing Depth (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Communications (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Construction and Maintenence (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cooks and Bakers (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dental Examination (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Electric (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Changing a Number One Stack (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Engineering (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fleet Marine Theatre staff (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Galley (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Galley (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Squadron Office (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Intelligence (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Library (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Line Crew at Work (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Machine Shop (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mechanic-Aircrewmen (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Physical Examination (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cooks and Bakers (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Metalsmiths (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mess (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Officers' Mess (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ordnance Aircrewmen (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Parachute Maintenance (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Parachute Riggers (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Operations (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ordinance (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Loading Rockets (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photo Section (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photography (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Squadron Members at the Sea (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Plumbing Shop (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Police Shed (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Post Office (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Projectionists (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Acting assistant quartermaster (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Acting assistant quartermaster (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Radio-Radar Shop (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Red Cross Unit (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Transportation (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Turret Shop (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Water Supply (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Fleet Marine Theater (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Front Area (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Officers' Club Veranda (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Senior NCO Barracks (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Officers' Club (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Barracks and Showers (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Squadron Area (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Enlisted Men's Barracks (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Recreation Hall (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Barracks and Storage Building (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Commanding and Executive Officer's Quarters (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Transportation Area (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Squadron Sign (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Isdland Softball Champions (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Trojans (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Baseball Team (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Basketball Team (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Officers' Club (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Recreation Hall (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Basketball Game (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Beergarden (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Arsenic and Old Lace (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Arsenic and Old Lace (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Forest Rangers (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Horizontal Bar (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Ping-Pong (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Rings (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Rings (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Squadron League Volleyball (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Amber-Spicer crew (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Riblet-Thomas crew (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Clenn-Kingman Crew (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Danser-Crowley Crew (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Barton-Litzau Crew (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Calder-Haroldson Crew (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Feakins-Varner Crew (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hanckock-Davis Crew (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Brotherton-Cooper Crew (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Youngren-Haselnus Crew (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Allen-Simmons crew (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Bennett-Mileson crew (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Cotton-Holtvedt Crew (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Love-Houston Crew (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Feid-Padach Crew (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Jackson-Saving Crew (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Newton-Spaulding Crew (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Twohy-Parks Crew (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Ligon-Malone Crew (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - McMillin-Meschke Crew (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Shipping Lane Patrol (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Shipping Lane Patrol (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Shipping Lane Patrol (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Work on the line (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Tent city (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Island Chapel (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Squadrons' sports (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Certificate of clearance (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Interior of Officers Club veranda (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Recreation area (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Medical and Dental (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Radio-Radar (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Darkroom (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Executive officer (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Carpenter shop (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Parachute loft (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Schatan-Crews crew (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Work on the line (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Line machanics and plane captains (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Nevils-Manning crew (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Cunningham-Kline crew (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Rogers-Noble crew (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Smith-Beggs crew (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Cleaning the canon (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Police (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Cleaning the canon (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Loading rockets (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Contemplative squadron member (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Returning to Majuro (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Pacific Atoll
  Fifty-four small black and white photographs in this series depict Japanese soldiers surrendering to American Marines, and the daily life of island natives on an unidentified atoll in the Marshall Islands. While a number of these pictures have typed captions glued on the bottom of the print, the names of people given in the captions are mostly satirical. This series also includes photographs of dead bodies after a battle, and some negatives.
  - approximately 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1-54)
- Tarawa
  Twenty-four small black and white photographs in this series depict Japanese soldiers surrendering to American Marines, and the daily life of island natives on an unidentified atoll in the Marshall Islands. While a number of these pictures have typed captions glued on the bottom of the print, the names of people given in the captions are mostly satirical. This series also includes photographs of dead bodies after a battle, and some negatives.
  - July 13, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - approximately 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3-24)
- Miscellaneous
  This series includes miscellaneous photographs and other materials. The front sections of the Houston Chronicle and Houston Post with headlines about the bombing of Pearl Harbor are part of this series.
  - Nov. 26, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - July, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - undated (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - July 20, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Dec. 7, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Dec. 8, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 31-32)
  - undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Nov. 14, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Nov. 16, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - [1886] (Box 4, Folder 36)